The Victor D'Amico Papers
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
- Series IX. Speeches and Writings, 1926-1982 (bulk 1938-1970)
  - Typescripts and copies, Undated; "We learn about the elements of design,” "Art experience reaches beyond the classroom" (Box 59, Folder IX.7)
  - "The New Decade", Undated; Manuscript and photocopied typescript (Box 59, Folder IX.8)
  - “A proposed project on the place of the crafts in general education”, Undated; Includes manuscript, two typescripts (Box 59, Folder IX.9)
  - Tears, 1926; Poetry collection, published by Palette Printing Company, Inc., New York: photocopy (Box 59, Folder IX.10)
  - Creative Teaching in Art(1 of 5), 1938-1941; Correspondence with publisher International Textbook Company. Includes contract (10/2/1939) with book’s original title Youthful Artists (Box 59, Folder IX.11)
  - Creative Teaching in Art(2 of 5), 1942; Correspondence with publisher International Textbook Company (Box 59, Folder IX.12)
  - Creative Teaching in Art(3 of 5), 1943-1944; Correspondence with publisher International Textbook Company (Box 60, Folder IX.13)
  - Creative Teaching in Art(4 of 5), 1945-1953; Correspondence with publisher International Textbook Company (Box 60, Folder IX.14)
  - Creative Teaching in Art(5 of 5), 1954-1972; Report of sales, credits, and royalties from publisher International Textbook Company (Box 60, Folder IX.15)
  - Creative Teaching in Art, [1940s]; Images used in book: b/w prints, transparencies (Box 60, Folder IX.16)
  - School and Home: Guidance Issue, 1941; Published by the Parents and Teachers Association of the Ethical Culture Schools: contains D'Amico chapter "Guidance through the arts" (Box 60, Folder IX.17)
  - Conference presentations, 1946, 1948, 1960, 1964; " ‘A’ is for art; art is for living," "[An] educational revolution and art," NY State Art Teachers Convention; "Art education in the new renaissance," Southeastern Arts Association; "Art: a human necessity,” presented at National Committee on Art Education conference and published in School Arts(carbon typed draft and clipping) (Box 60, Folder IX.18)
  - Publisher correspondence, 1947-1957; Royalty statements and related correspondence from publishers (Box 60, Folder IX.19)
  - Art Education Today, 1948; Published by Bureau of Publications, Teachers College, and edited by Edwin Ziegfeld, Virginia Murphy, and D'Amico (Box 60, Folder IX.20)
  - Conference participation, 1950-1960; Correspondence re: attendance and speeches (Box 60, Folder IX.21)
  - Notes for speeches and presentations, 1951, undated; Typed and handwritten (Box 60, Folder IX.22)
  - Undated photocopied manuscript, clipping, 1951, undated; "The arts and creativity in the lives of children and youth”; “A generation of esthetes,”LIFE Magazine (Box 60, Folder IX.23)
  - Clippings, 1952, 1960, 1961; From and about schools programs, including correspondence with Evander Childs High School, from which D'Amico had graduated in 1924 (Box 60, Folder IX.24)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1960; Re: reprinting published material (Box 60, Folder IX.25)
  - Clippings, reprints, draft, April 1953; September 14, 1956; 1960; 1962; "Are we jeopardizing the child's creative growth?,"Eastern Arts Association Art Education Bulletin; "Le attivita educative del Museo d’Arte Moderna di New York,"La Voce dell' America, USIS; introduction to National Committee on Art Education publication; "A creative art education workshop in a vacation setting,"School Arts (Box 60, Folder IX.26)
  - "An evaluation of creative education", November 1955; Presentation at New York University concurrent with an exhibition of art by children in MoMA's People's Art Center classes (Paintings Collages Constructions by Children): draft and typed presentation, correspondence, b/w photograph (Box 60, Folder IX.27)
  - Unattributed typed drafts, post 1957; undated; Profile of Mabel D'Amico's art; address list of MoMA staff and patrons (Box 60, Folder IX.28)
  - Original and photocopied drafts from meetings of National Committee on Art Education, 1957-1959; "Changing Concepts in Art Education," regional meeting; "Coming Events Cast Their Shadows," 16th annual conference; "Looking Ahead," 17th annual conference; "Teaching - A Lost Art" (Box 60, Folder IX.29)
  - Original and photocopied drafts and published articles, 1958-1959, undated; "Understanding children's creativeness,"The Instructor; "Help your child develop a seeing eye,”House Beautiful; "Coming events cast their shadows," originally presented at National Committee on Art Education 16th annual conference, adapted for publication in School Arts; New York University Meeting on Creativity; "Cooperation vs. affiliation"; "Art education in the United States” (Box 60, Folder IX.30)
  - Typed and handwritten notes and drafts, 1959, 1962-1963; Includes comments to National Conference Committee; undated review of film "Approach to art teaching"; Christmas message; "Arts and Crafts or Arts and Craftsmanship,”Craft Horizons (Box 60, Folder IX.31)
  - "Art for children, parents, adults, schools”, [1960s]; Subtitled “The philosophy and program of the Department of Education, The Museum of Modern Art”: hand-emended carbon copy (Box 61, Folder IX.32)
  - Creative writings, 1960, undated; Manuscripts and typescripts; includes text for Christmas program 1960 (Box 61, Folder IX.33)
  - Typed drafts, 1960, 1961, undated; Includes "Quality and Excellence in Art," delivered at Exhibition of the Work of Independent Schools, St. James Church (Box 61, Folder IX.34)
  - Statements on art education, 1960-1970, undated; Manuscript, typescript, and clippings on teaching techniques and theory (Box 61, Folder IX.35)
  - Drafts for untitled book, [1960]; Handwritten versions of some material in folders IX.38-42 (Box 61, Folder IX.36)
  - Drafts for untitled book, [1960]; Chapter I. Teaching is an art: edited typed draft (Box 61, Folder IX.37)
  - Drafts for untitled book, [1960]; Chapter I. Teaching is an art: typed draft, two carbons (Box 61, Folder IX.38)
  - Drafts for untitled book, [1960]; Chapter II. Fundamentals of art education: typed draft, three carbons (Box 61, Folder IX.39)
  - Drafts for untitled book, [1960]; Chapter III. The discovery of the creative child: typed draft, two carbons (Box 61, Folder IX.40)
  - Drafts for untitled book, [1960]; Chapter IV. The dynamic role of the art teacher: two typed versions, each paginated differently, and one carbon (Box 61, Folder IX.41)
  - Drafts for untitled book, [1960]; "Chapter V.?". Our art heritage: The problem of teaching art appreciation: two typed drafts, three carbons (Box 61, Folder IX.42)
  - Draft chapter for untitled book, [1960]; [Chapter V]. Our art heritage: The problem of teaching art appreciation: handwritten and typed drafts (Box 62, Folder IX.43)
  - Drafts for untitled book, [1960]; Includes "Development of the progress of an art teacher" and unorganized handwritten drafts of [1960] typed versions (Box 62, Folder IX.44)
  - Art History section of Richards Topical Encyclopedia, 1961; Correspondence, outline re: planned topical encyclopedia to be published by Grolier (Box 62, Folder IX.45)
  - "Art Education in the United States", 1961; The Voice of America Forum Lectures, 7 (Box 62, Folder IX.46)
  - Clippings and drafts, 1961-1967; "Crafts in education: Institute of Modern Art," "The object: lost and found,"Craft Horizons; "How to choose an art school,"Art Voices; "Developing creative sensitivity in children,"Junior League Magazine; “The exciting world of art,"Parents' Magazine (Box 62, Folder IX.47)
  - WQXR radio interview, January 24, 1962; Questions and draft answers (Box 62, Folder IX.48)
  - Conference presentations, 1962; "The ideal educational program for a museum of art," North Carolina Museum of Art; "Can art be taught?," Philadelphia Museum College of Art (Box 62, Folder IX.49)
  - "Does creative education have a future?", August 27, 1963; An essay based on an address given at the conference of the International Society for Education through Art, Montreal, Canada: six copies (Box 62, Folder IX.50)
  - Correspondence with publishers, 1964-1972; Re: current and possible future articles (Box 62, Folder IX.51)
  - Manuscript and typescript, [1964]; "Toys, play and the child" (event identified only as "Rochester"), including list of slides for Children’s Art Carnival (Box 62, Folder IX.52)
  - Found Objects, State University College at Buffalo, February-March 1965; Draft text of catalogue for exhibition (Box 62, Folder IX.53)
  - "The Creative Eye,"Parents Magazine, December 1965-January 1966; Typed draft, correspondence (Box 62, Folder IX.54)
  - Conference presentations (1 of 2), 1965-1969; "New concepts for the arts of our time,” Southeastern Division, Minnesota Education Association; "Art education and the pursuit of excellence," Minnesota Education Association; "Developing children for a creative world," Symposium on child art, University of California, Berkeley; "New art concepts for a new era," Rochester Institute of Technology; "The trend toward trends in contemporary art education,” New York University symposium; "The future role of the Department of Education of the Museum of Modern Art," unidentified event; "New concepts for the arts of our time," Minnesota Art Education Association: 1965 (Box 62, Folder IX.55)
  - Conference presentations (2 of 2), 1965-1969; "The quality of excellence,” Georgia Art Education Association; "Is modern art anti-human?,” Miami Dade Junior College; "Art is for the living,” University of Miami, Coral Gables: manuscript and typescript; untitled lecture, Staten Island Children's Theater Association; "Museum art education in crisis,” ISAE meeting on the role of art museums, held at MoMA May 22, 1969 (Box 63, Folder IX.56)
  - Typescripts, May 1966, undated; "What price creative youth?”; "A plea and an argument for stimulating creative art education in our schools”; "The art of teaching art”; "Unfinished business”; "Commentary - review”; "Creative characteristics (6-7 years) from tape"; "Art education today: millennium [sic] or mirage?": includes both typed draft and published version in Art Education (Box 63, Folder IX.57)
  - Tearsheets and correspondence, March 1968, April 1969, October 1970; "The Art Barge – a creative adventure in art education”; "The multifaceted art teacher in a multimedia environment"; "The Children's Art Caravan,”Arts and Activities (Box 63, Folder IX.58)
  - Publishing agreement, 1968, 1971; Among D’Amico, Arlette Buchman, and Harry N. Abrams for Drawing - Exploring Line (Box 63, Folder IX.59)
  - Miami University, January-June 1974, 1978-1979; Autobiographical lecture (1974) and other visits to Miami University: original typescript and photocopy, correspondence, itinerary (Box 63, Folder IX.60)
  - "Art for human survival", April 1974; In Festschrift: 100 Years of Education for the Arts published by Syracuse University College of Visual and Performing Arts: three copies (Box 63, Folder IX.61)
  - Notes for teacher training classes, 1979-1982; For "Met Class" and LIATA (Long Island Art Teachers Association): handwritten on the backs of envelopes (Box 63, Folder IX.62)
- Series X. Personal, 1945-1985, 1987, 2003
  The series consists of personal materials either created by D'Amico or given to him, including correspondence, writings, invitations, as well as honors and awards that he received.
  The series is arranged in two subseries:
  Subseries X.A. Personal Records and Correspondence,1945, 1946, 1951-1985, 2003
  Subseries X.B. Awards and Honors,1951-1953, 1964-1981, 1987
  - Subseries X.A. Personal Records and Correspondence, 1945, 1946, 1951-1985, 2003
    - Two unlabeled Super 8 film reels, Undated; NOTE: These two Super 8 films have been transferred to the Museum's Film Study Center which has the proper facilities for storing and screening them. Researchers should contact the Center for further information. Access may be denied due to the films' physical condition. (Box 63, Folder X.A.1)
    - Correspondence, 1944, 1945; Includes student recommendations (Box 63, Folder X.A.2)
    - Correspondence, 1951-1958; Includes Alex Lord correspondence re: Sag Harbor house (Box 63, Folder X.A.3)
    - Sketches and plans, 1958; Unidentified pencil sketches (Box 63, Folder X.A.4)
    - “Xmas 1959, moon child, Becker party”, 7" film reel; NOTE: This 7" film reel been transferred to the Museum's Film Study Center, which has the proper facilities for storing and screening them. Researchers should contact the Study Center for further information. Access may be denied due to the film's physical condition. (Box 63, Folder X.A.5)
    - Poems to Victor and Mabel, 1960; Poems by students and others, possibly collected for a festschrift or other homage (Box 63, Folder X.A.6)
    - Album of Motivations, 1962-1969; Presented to D’Amico by "Peter," possibly as a retirement gift: sheets removed from mylar-sleeved looseleaf album (Box 63, Folder X.A.7)
    - Letters and notes to D’Amico, 1962-1982, 1984, 1986; Includes some correspondence re: dinner in honor of D’Amico, National Arts Club (11/17/1982) (Box 63, Folder X.A.8)
    - Drawing and note from Stewart Stern, June 1968 (Box 71, Folder X.A.9*)
    - John Markov, 1968; Candid wedding photographs: color slides (Box 63, Folder X.A.10)
    - Drawings and sketches, circa 1970; Includes sketch of Art Barge with measurements (Box 63, Folder X.A.11)
    - D’Amico resumés, 1960s-1970s (Box 63, Folder X.A.12)
    - Biographies, 1960s-1970s; Various typed and handwritten summaries of D’Amico’s accomplishments; list of famous students including MoMA curator William Rubin, photographer Diane Arbus, broadcaster Barbara Walters (Box 64, Folder X.A.13)
    - Correspondence, June-September 1971; Re: Carolyn Yates article on Hallmark's Kaleidoscope project in Art Education and program's indebtedness to D’Amico's teaching methods (Box 64, Folder X.A.14)
    - Letters protesting planned local developments, and closing of East Hampton Medical Center, 1972, 1977; Some personal from D’Amico, some with signatures of artists and students (Box 64, Folder X.A.15)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1982; Includes thank you sent to guests at November 17, 1982 honorary dinner, requests for letters of recommendations, thank yous for personal letters; correspondents include MoMA Trustees Henry Allen Moe, Mrs. Walter Hochschild (Box 64, Folder X.A.16)
    - Morgagni Medical Society dinner dance, May 1975; Clipping with photograph of D'Amico and other participants, information on Morgagni medal (Box 64, Folder X.A.17)
    - "Victor D'Amico - creative powerhouse", 1977; Based on interview with D’Amico by Marcia Chaiet: carbon typescript (Box 64, Folder X.A.18)
    - Poems and stories by Marlene Tartaglione, Fall 1978; October 15, 1981; With letter Tartaglione-D’Amico (10/15/1981) (Box 64, Folder X.A.19)
    - Victor D'Amico - 50 Years of Humanizing Art: exhibition at Guild Hall (Easthampton, NY), 1978-1979; B/w negatives of exhibition panels; color slides of art works (Box 64, Folder X.A.20)
    - Victor D'Amico - 50 Years of Humanizing Art: exhibition at Guild Hall (Easthampton, NY), 1978-1979; B/w prints of wall panel (Box 64, Folder X.A.21)
    - Victor D'Amico - 50 Years of Humanizing Art: exhibition at Guild Hall (Easthampton, NY), September-October 1979; Catalogue: three copies (Box 64, Folder X.A.22)
    - Victor D'Amico - 50 Years of Humanizing Art: exhibition at Guild Hall (Easthampton, NY), 1979; Guest book for opening; testamentary letters: correspondents include MoMA Painting and Sculpture Department director William Rubin, educator Robert Iglehart, gallerist Marion F.T. Johnson (Box 64, Folder X.A.23)
    - Victor D'Amico - 50 Years of Humanizing Art: exhibition at Guild Hall (Easthampton, NY), 1979; Invitation, copies of guest book, clippings, correspondence (Box 64, Folder X.A.24)
    - Lois A. Berggren interview with D'Amico, photocopied articles, correspondence, 1979-1980; Supporting material for master's thesis structured as festschrift (see folders X.A.33, 34); Berggren had been a student of Mabel D'Amico's (Box 64, Folder X.A.25)
    - Items sent by D’Amico to Miami University (Ohio) for inclusion in their Archives, 1979-1981; Lists, photocopies (Box 65, Folder X.A.26)
    - Portraits of Victor by his pupils, [1980s]; Ink wash, marker on paper (Box 65, Folder X.A.27)
    - Letters and notes to D’Amico, 1981-1984 (Box 65, Folder X.A.28)
    - Invitation to dinner in his honor, from Victor D’Amico Institute of Art board members, August 13, 1982; Hand-lettered (Box 73, Folder X.A.29*)
    - National Arts Club tribute dinner, New York City, November 17, 1982; Guest book, invitation, typed comments from Elizabeth Fuller (Box 65, Folder X.A.30)
    - ALS D’Amico-Arlette Buchman (12/15/1982) answering her questions about people influential in his life, December 15, 1982; These included MoMA Directors Alfred H. Barr, Jr. and René D’Harnoncourt, MoMA Trustee Nelson A. Rockefeller (Box 65, Folder X.A.31)
    - "Victor D'Amico: His Sources and Influences," by Lois A. Berggren, Spring 1984; Photocopy of edited typescript, version 1 (Box 65, Folder X.A.32)
    - "Victor D'Amico: His Sources and Influences," by Lois A. Berggren, Spring 1984; Photocopy of edited typescript, version 2 (Box 65, Folder X.A.33)
    - The Dr. Victor D'Amico Cat Book, 1984-1985; Pencil and marker sketches, text (Box 65, Folder X.A.34)
    - TLS Chris Kohan-Arlette Buchman, November 10, 2003; Re: materials about D’Amico she had sent to Art Barge (Box 65, Folder X.A.35)
  - Subseries X.B. Awards and Honors, 1951-1953, 1964-1981, 1987
    - State University of New York Institute of Applied Arts and Sciences: appointment to Advisory Commission for Commercial Art; Evander Childs High School: Distinguished Alumnus Award, 1951, 1952; Originals and photoreproductions of awards (Box 65, Folder X.B.1)
    - The Girl Scout National Organization: certificate of appreciation, July 16, 1953; Correspondence, photoreproductions of award (Box 71, Folder X.B.2*)
    - State University of New York College at Buffalo: citation of merit, April 30, 1964; Original award (removed from presentation case) and photoreproductions (Box 71, Folder X.B.3*)
    - Philadelphia Museum College of Art: doctor of fine arts degree, June 8, 1964; Photoreproductions of award (Box 73, Folder X.B.4*)
    - Pratt Institute: certificate of appreciation; New York State Art Teacher’s Association: bronze plaque; National Gallery of Art: medal for distinguished service to education in art, 1964, 1966, 1968; Includes clipping, photo of D’Amico with First Lady Claudia Taylor (Lady Bird) Johnson, at National Gallery (Box 65, Folder X.B.5)
    - Miami University School of Fine Arts: achievement award, May 2, 1974; June 24, 1975; Original award (removed from presentation case) and photoreproductions; correspondence (Box 71, Folder X.B.6*)
    - City School District of New York: certificates of service in the voluntary after-school professional development program; Children’s Art Carnival’s D’Amico award; New York City Art Teacher’s Association’s Victor D’Amico art educators award, 1978-1981; Originals, photographs, and photoreproduction of awards (Box 65, Folder X.B.7)
    - City of New York: citation of honor, April 30, 1979; Presented "in recognition of your outstanding contributions and pioneering efforts promoting the Humanistic Approach in Art Education in the [sic] American Society": photoreproductions of citation (Box 71, Folder X.B.8*)
    - Long Island Art Teachers' Association: art teacher of our generation award; World Gratitude Day, 1979; Originals and photoreproductions, color print and slide (Box 71, Folder X.B.9*)
    - Dallas Museum of Art: teacher in-service in memory of D’Amico, October-November 1987; Includes reprinted comments from MoMA memorial by Director Richard Oldenburg and others (Box 65, Folder X.B.10)
- Series XI. Printed Materials, 1936-1995
  The series includes books, magazines, catalogues, and clippings not produced by MoMA or written by D'Amico. Some are related to D'Amico projects at the Museum, and most to education in general and other subjects. These appear to have been collected both in D'Amico's office at MoMA and later, perhaps by his widow Mabel.
  - Clippings, reprints, program, 1936-1938, 1953, 1955, 1961, 1964-1966; Includes “Art,”Time Magazine; “Fine Arts,”Review of Educational Research; "Homemaker's Forum,” New Jersey State College Extension Service; "Action on West 53rd Street" parts I and II,The New Yorker; “The time for art,”Today’s Secretary; “Children’s Art Carnival,”Spain; “Creativity in your classroom,”Grade Teacher; “Appreciation and creation through construction,”The Instructor (Box 66, Folder XI.1)
  - The first 50 Years, 1898-1948: Report of the superintendent of schools, 50th Annual Report of the Superintendent of Schools, Board of Education, The City of New York (Box 66, Folder XI.2)
  - Catalogues, reports, 1949-1950, 1961, 1972, 1978; "Art Treasures from the Vienna Collections, lent by the Austrian government"; Supplement to the annual report 1961, Institute of International Education;Lenore Tawney: A personal world(inscribed to D’Amico);Looking south: Latin American art in New York collections, 1972 (Box 66, Folder XI.3)
  - UNESCO album:Human Rights(1/2), 1950; Individual pages of exhibition album, removed from presentation portfolio (Box 71, Folder XI.4*)
  - UNESCO album:Human Rights(2/2), 1950; Individual pages of exhibition album, removed from presentation portfolio (Box 71, Folder XI.5*)
  - Scuola Mazzon, 1952; Art work by children, published by Edizione scuola e arte; edition 195 of a limited run; probably received as part of Children’s Art Carnival in Italy (Box 66, Folder XI.6)
  - Lists of best picture books of the year, from The New York Times, 1952-1959; Clippings, typed lists (Box 66, Folder XI.7)
  - Articles and reprints, 1953, 1958, 1966, undated; "Art education for scientist and engineer" in Education and the Imagination in Science and Art(two copies); "Art therapy at an outpatient clinic,”Psychiatry; "Wiltwyck: Home of the wild ones,”Reader's Digest; "Report on the arts and humanities institutes of 1966,”Compass report; "Psychiatric art therapy manual,” District of Columbia General Hospital (Box 66, Folder XI.8)
  - Clippings, mostly from New Jersey newspapers, re:Developing Creativeness In Children[MoMA Exh. #575, March 15-April 17, 1955], April 1957, April 1958; The exhibition was loaned to the Montclair Art Museum; includes a clipping on the Children's Art Carnival in Brussels (Box 66, Folder XI.9)
  - Art Therapy in a Children's Community, 1958; Book subtitled “A study of the function of art therapy in the treatment program of Wiltwyck School for Boys” by Edith Kramer (Box 66, Folder XI.10)
  - How One Three-Year-Old Girl Taught Herself to Draw, 1959; by Ronda Kellog: unbound printed sheets in folder (Box 66, Folder XI.11)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings on creativity, 1961 (Box 66, Folder XI.12)
  - Voice of America Forum lectures 1, 6, 10, 12, 14, 16, 17, [1961]; “The visual arts in mid-century America,” Lamar Dodd; “The role of the art historian,” Millard Weiss; “Prints,” Carl Zigrosser; “Sculpture,” Henry Hope; “Decorative arts and crafts,” David R. Campbell; “Modernist painting,” Clement Greeberg; “The relation of abstract art to nature,” John I. H. Baur; “The arts and their interrelations,” Thomas Munro (Box 66, Folder XI.13)
  - Reprints, 1961, 1963; "The decision to fail,” Bruno Bettelheim,The School Review(inscribed "Cordially/ Bruno"); "The Second Annual Reed & Barton Design Lecture: Matter and intrinsic form,” Marcel Breuer (Box 67, Folder XI.14)